Guide to the French Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1927-1956 UA.40.8
ULS Archives & Special Collections
French Nationality Room Committee Collection
1927-1956
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. French Nationality Room Committee
UA.40.8
2 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
This collection of records from the French Nationality Classroom Committee dates from 1927 to 1943 and contains information regarding the development of the French Nationality Room at the University of Pittsburgh's Cathedral of Learning.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection of records from the French Nationality Classroom Committee dates from 1927 to 1943 and contains information regarding the development of the French Nationality Room at the University of Pittsburgh's Cathedral of Learning. Included are correspondence, meeting minutes, and financial records of the committee which document the development and fundraising efforts for the classroom. Also included is correspondence with architects, blue prints, and running memos concerning the room's construction. Newspaper clippings and other publicity materials chronicle the opening of the classroom. There are also several photographs of the committee, the finished classroom, artwork that inspired the room design, and events and guests.
History
The idea of a French Nationality Classroom was first proposed by Chancellor John Bowman and the "Alliance Français" in the spring of 1929. They decided the room would represent the French Regency of Louis XIV and Louis XV and Harold Le Baron, a New York architect, completed the preliminary sketches.
Due to the Great Depression, plans for the room were put on hold until 1931. Upon hearing that the French room was to be omitted from the Cathedral of Learning due to a lack of funding, Madame Liard, a member of the Secretatiat of the Institut Internationale de Cooperation Intellectuelle, proposed that the French government fund the room. Ambassador Monsieur Paul Claudel approved the funding and also requested that the room's theme be changed to a French Gothic style. There were many groups and events that aided in the funding of the room, such as the Bal Tabarin gala, which would later become an esteemed Winter social event tradition. Other events included programs of music promoting French-American affairs, bridge nights, and a "Gay Soiree."
The first French classroom committee was formed in 1932 comprised of Dr. Alexandre Mage as president; Mrs. Raoul Mayer, Mr. Adolph Pletincks, Mr. Louis Harter, and Mr. Emile Majerus as vice presidents; Mr. Louis Celestin as Secretary; and Treasurer Glenn McKee. The committee was reformed in 1936 and Mage became honorary chairman and Celestin became chairman. Dr. Whitford Shelton was elected secretary-treasurer. A subcommittee was created to consult on the room's new plan to use the French Empire period as the most academic theme.
French architect Jacques Carlu was selected to prepare the final drawings of the room. The new Empire period chosen for the room design incorporates elements from ancient Egypt, Greece, and Italy, which was rediscovered by the French during the conquests of Napoleon. These elements are represented in the classroom through the Egyptian griffins and Greek acanthus sprigs carved as ornaments. The windows in the room face the Heinz Chapel, which is also built within the style of the French Gothic Period.
The room opened on January 23, 1943, during the same time France was being invaded by Germany during World War II. The room was used as a symbol of hope for the committee. As final touches were being added, the committee chose to carve the French coat of arms above the door, encapsulating the French motto, "Liberte, Egalite, et Fraternite" meaning Liberty, Equality, and Brotherhood.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by the Nationality Rooms Program Office in 2014.
University of Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. French Nationality Room Committee; Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- General Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- General Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- General Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- General Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- General Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Opening Ceremony, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Article by Louis C. Celestin, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Deed of Gift, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- French Room Blueprint, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- French Room Drawing, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photograph: Informal Opening of French Classroom, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
- Photograph: Aids at French Classroom Opening, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Photograph: Dr. John Bowman Accepting Key, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Photograph: Key Bearer at Informal Opening, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Photograph: Mrs. Paul Baudry (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Photograph: French Room Committee, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Photograph: Mr. Wilfred P. Allard Making Presentation (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Photograph: Nationality Room Book Illustrations, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Photograph: Mr. Jean Marc Thanking Mr. Wilfred P. Allard, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Photograph: Mr. Wilfred P. Allard Presenting Nationality Rooms Book, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Photograph: Presentation of Daum Vase to French Room Committee, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Photograph: French Concert Benefit for Scholarship, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Photograph: Presentation of Stipend from French Cultural Affairs Office, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Photograph: French Scholarship Benefit Concert, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Photograph: French Embassador, Charles Lucet Visits French Room, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Photograph: French Ambassador Charles Lucet Signs Guestbook, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Photograph: French Ambassador in Chancellor's Office, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Photograph: French Ambassador Charles Lucet Visit, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Photograph: French Ambassador Charles Lucet Card, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Photograph: French Classroom (Box 1, Folder 44-47)
- Photograph: French Room Committee, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Photograph: French Room Committee, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Photograph: Decorations Committee (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Photograph: Original French Room Plan (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
- Photograph: Head of Department of Modern Languages, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Photograph: French Classroom Entrance Door (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Photograph: Mademoiselle de la Vorge (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photograph: Bourdon- Portrait of Man (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photograph: Prudhon- Madame Barbin Walbourne (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photograph: Nattier - Langue White Gown (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photograph: Fragonard - La Coquette et Le Jouvenceau (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photograph: Bouchard - Le Bain de Venus (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photograph: David - Head of Androiuvdie (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photograph: Gruze J.N.B. Varenne (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photograph: Claude Lorrain - View of Seaport (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photograph: Chardin, Le Tapeur (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Photograph: Fragonard - Shepard in Landscape (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Photograph: Poussin - Thesus Discovering his Father's Sword (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photograph: Robert - Enfants Jouaut Duistepered Emmenouiee (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Photograph: Pater - Les Avoeusc Indiscrets (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photograph: Bouchard - Les Jeunes Bergers (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Photograph: French Interior (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Photograph: Unidentified Woman (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Publicity Materials, 1935-1943 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1932-1943 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Christmas Supper Event, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Fontainbleu School Booklet, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Committee for the French Classroom in the Cathedral of Learning Volume, 1927-1943 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Running Memos, 1927-1943; 1.
  - Minutes, 1932-1943; 2.
  - Financial Statments, 1933-1942; 3.
  - List of Donors, 4.
  - Subscribers to Bal Tabarin, 1935; 5.